Alan Swallow Papers
Alan Swallow Papers
1934-1964
Swallow, Alan, 1915-1966.
3.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, poet, publisher. Correspondence (1942-1964); manuscript poems and essays; and published materials, including articles and clippings by and about Swallow, book reviews, poems, and stories by Swallow, and photographs. Correspondents include Louise Bogan, Weldon Kees, Archibald MacLeish, Henry Miller, Marianne Moore, Isaac Bashevis Singer, Wallace Stevens, Allen Tate, Robert Penn Warren, William Carlos Williams, and others.
148692
Biographical History
Alan Swallow (1915-1966) was an American poet, editor, teacher, and publisher.
Swallow was born February 11, 1915, in Powell, Wyoming. He received a B.A. degree from the University of Wyoming in 1937 and an M.A. degree from Louisiana State University in 1939. At LSU he studied under Robert Penn Warren and Cleanth Brooks. He was an instructor at the University of New Mexico (1940-1942) and associate professor of English at Western State College (1942-1943). He then taught at the University of Denver as assistant professor(1948-1954). He also directed the writing program at U. of Denver and from 1947 to 1953 was director of the University Press. In 1940, Swallow became the founder, owner, and single employee of his publishing firm, Alan Swallow, Publisher. He sought to promote the poetry and fiction of contemporary writers who are often unrecognized by the larger commercial publishers. His list included J.V. Cunningham, Thomas McGrath, Janet Lewis, and the more well known Yvor Winters and Allen Tate. Swallow has also written and published several books of poems and has edited anthologies of poetry and of prose. He lectured at various writers' conferences and was a member of the Western Writers of America, Colorado Authors League, Denver Westerners, and American Civil Liberties Union. He died on November 27, 1966 in Denver, Colorado.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alan Swallow Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts and published material.
Correspondence includes authors, editors, publisher, and fellow poets. Notable individuals include Louise Bogan, Jane Grabhorn (Grabhorn Press), Archibald MacLeish, Henry Miller, Marianne Moore, Isaac Bashevis Singer, Wallace Stevens, Allen Tate, Robert Penn Warren, and William Carlos Williams.
Subject files contains conference and writers' workshop programs, legal material relating to the Supreme Court case involving Henry Miller's Tropic of Cancer, photographs of Swallow, printing specimens, and various trade lists, mailing pieces and notices from Alan Swallow, Publisher, and his subsidiary presses (e.g. Sage Books).
Manuscripts consists of typescripts of books, essays, poems, and other writings by Swallow and by others.
Published material consists of articles, book reviews, newspaper clippings (Swallow had a regular newspaper column), pamphlets, poems, and short stories by Swallow. In addition, there are articles about Swallow, magazines published by him and by others, books written by others and some published by Swallow, pamphlets published by Swallow, pamphlets written and published by others, and miscellaneous magazines. Some of the articles, books, and pamphlets are inscribed by their authors to Swallow.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Subject files and manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by subject or title respectively. Published material is subdivided by type and then arranged in alphabetical order by type, except for newspaper clippings and poems by A.S. which are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
See also the
William Claire Collection Relating to Alan Swallow
.
Separated Material
A large number of books have been removed from the collection and catalogued separately. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Publishing, printing and book arts; Bogan, Louise, 1897-1970.; Brittin, Norman A.; Brown, Bob.; Coleman, Carroll.; Cunningham, J. V. (James Vincent), 1911-1985.; Davidson, Gustav, 1895-1971.; Decker, James A.; De Jong, David Cornel, 1901-1967.; Elliott, George P., 1918-1980.; Fitzell, Lincoln, 1903-1958.; Frederick, John T. (John Towner), 1893-1975.; Gold, Herbert, 1924-; Goll, Yvan, 1891-1950.; Gordon, Caroline, 1895-1981.; Grabhorn, Jane Bissell.; Kees, Weldon, 1914-1955.; Kunitz, Stanley, 1905-2006.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Miles, Josephine, 1911-1985.; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980.; Mills, Clark, 1913-; Moon, Bucklin, 1911-1984.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Moore, Merrill, 1903-1957.; Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1904-1991.; Stanford, Ann.; Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955.; Swallow, Alan, 1915-1966.; Taggard, Genevieve, 1894-1948.; Tate, Allen, 1899-1979.; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-1989.; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963.; American literature -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Poets, American.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Articles.; Books.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Journals (periodicals); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.; Poets.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alan Swallow, 1964-1966.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - American Poet, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Bogan, Louise, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Robert, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Bruce Humphries Inc., 1943 (Box 1)
  - B, misc, 1943 (Box 1)
    Brittin, Norman A,; Broomell, Myron H.
  - Ciardi, John, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Carroll, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Caukin, Helen Ferguson, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Clark, Walter van Tilburg, 1943 (Box 1)
  - The Colt Press (Bill Roth), 1942 (Box 1)
  - Cunningham, J. V., 1942; undated (Box 1)
  - Davidson, Gustav, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Decker, James A., 1942; 1947; includes cancelled check from AS (Box 1)
  - De Jong, David Cornel, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Doubleday, Doran & Co., 1943 (Box 1)
  - Dudgeon, Patrick Orpen, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Elman, Richard (Dick), 1961-1963; outgoing (Box 1)
  - E, misc., 1947; 1959 (Box 1)
    Elliott, George; Erno, Richard B.
  - Felton, George H., 1943 (Box 1)
  - Ferril, Thomas Hornsby, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Fitzell, Lincoln, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Frederick, John T., 1943 (Box 1)
  - F, misc., 1951; undated (Box 1)
    Fergusson, Harvey; Fox, Albertine
  - Grabhorn, Jane, 1943 (Box 1)
  - G, misc., 1943; 1946,; 1948,; undated (Box 1)
    Gold, Herb; Goll, Yvan; Gordon, Caroline; Griggs, Stephen Tolland
  - Hartman, Carl, 1964; outgoing; detailed three-page letter, almost an essay, on the novel as a genre and novel publishing (Box 1)
  - Horton, Ruth, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Hunter, Bonnie, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Kees, Weldon, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Kunitz, Stanley, 1943 (Box 1)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1943 (Box 1)
  - McGrath, Thomas, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Miller, Henry, circa 1948; includes letter from Miller's wife Lepska on his behalf (Box 1)
  - Mills, Clark, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Moon, Bucklin, See Doubleday, Doran & Co.
  - Moore, Marianne, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Moore, Merrill, 1942 (Box 1)
  - M-R, misc., 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    McGregor, J.S.T.[?]; Miles, Josephine; Montana State University; Moore, Nicholas; Rosenberg, Harold
  - Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Stevens, Wallace, 1943 (Box 1)
  - S, misc., 1943; 1964 (Box 1)
    Schevill, James; Stanford, Ann; Sutherland, Anne
  - Taggard, Genevieve, undated (Box 1)
  - Tate, Allen, 1943 (Box 1)
  - T-U, misc, 1943 (Box 1)
    Thomson, Rosamund Dargan; University of Buffalo; University of Nebraska Press
  - Van Doren, Mark, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Volkening, Henry, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1943; 1951 (Box 1)
  - W, misc., 1942-1943 (Box 1)
    Western State College; Wynn, Dudley
  - Unidentified, undated; outgoing; to multiple recipients, requesting assistance in publishing his work (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Conference and workshop programs (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Vardis, AS interview of Fisher (Box 2)
  - Greeting card (Box 2)
  - Legal contracts (Box 2)
  - Notes (Box 2)
  - Photographs, candid shots of AS alone and with others (Box 2)
  - Printer's specimen sheet, various examples of letterhead, AS and others (Box 1)
  - Trade lists, mailing pieces, advertisements, notices to authors - from A.S. (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - The Harvest Waits / Lorene Pearson, typescript with corrections, 659 pp.; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Stars Ploughed Under / Stephen Tolland Griggs, typescript carbon with corrections, approximately 500 pp. (Box 3)
  - Essays
    - [Untitled] / J.V. Cunningham, on his style (Box 3)
    - "The Death of the Novel and/or the Disappearing Audience" / Jarvis Thurston, typescript, 33 pp. (Box 3)
    - Foreword to unidentified book / Alan Swallow (Box 3)
  - Poems
    - Code, Grant H. / "Division", several poems and epigrams (Box 3)
    - Cunningham, J.V., several poems and epigrams (Box 3)
    - Damon, S.F. / "The Mad Huntsman" (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - "Poetry of the West" / Alan Swallow, several poems and epigrams (Box 3)
- Published material
  - Abstract of thesis by Alan Swallow (Box 4)
  - Articles
    - About Swallow (Box 4)
    - By Swallow, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - By others (Box 4)
  - Books
    - Curecanti, 1943; yearbook for Western State College (Box 4)
    - An editor's essays of two decades / Alan Swallow, 1948; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - Index to Little Magazines / Alan Swallow, H. Colgrave, A. Smith, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Moods in Melody / Jesse L. Kraft, 1962; signed and inscribed to Swallow (Box 5)
    - A Season of Grace / N. V. M. Gonzalez (Box 5)
    - Silver Souvenir / Poetry Society of Colorado, published by Alan Swallow (Box 5)
  - Book reviews
    - By Swallow, 1943; 1954 (Box 5)
      Reviews of Hill Wind (Kittredge) and God or Caesar? (Vardis Fisher)
  - Legal briefs
    - Smith v. California amica curiae brief, 1962; pertaining to lawsuit regarding Henry Miller's Tropic of Cancer, includes memo from Barney Rosset of Grove Press; Swallow and more than 100 others were co-signers of the brief (Box 5)
  - Magazines
    - Advance Guard #2 /Swallow Press, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Antiquarian Bookman, 1948-1950; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Evergreen Review #25 / Grove Press, 1962; issue contains "Freedom to Read" statement; Swallow and more than 100 others were co-signers (Box 5)
    - Foothills / University of Denver, 1946; creative writing class publication; AS was faculty advisor (Box 5)
    - Through the Leaves / Great Western Sugar Company, Jul 1941; contains article by Swallow's father, Edgar Swallow (Box 5)
    - Writing at Wyoming / University of Wyoming Dept. of English, 1963; AS was co-sponsor (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, A-Z, no discernible connection to AS (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About Swallow (Box 6)
    - About others (Box 6)
    - By Swallow, 1957; undated; 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets
    - By Alan Swallow (Box 6)
    - By others, published by Swallow (Box 6)
    - By others, some inscribed to Swallow (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
  - Poems
    - By Alan Swallow, in greeting card, Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
    - By Alan Swallow, 1934-1938; in various publications, including College Verse and New Mexico Quarterly; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - By Alan Swallow, 1939; 1941,; 1943,; 1949-1950,; 1957,; undated; in various publications, including College Verse and New Mexico Quarterly; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - By Genevieve Taggard, "To Tolstoy in Retrospect" signed (Box 7)
  - Publisher and bookseller catalogs
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Short stories
    - By Alan Swallow, 1951; "Golden Girl" in New Mexico Quarterly (Box 7)